Boker
tov בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, we'll talk after. Okay. I'm
just- we already starting. I'm already starting. Okay. All right. Boker tov
בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's daf דף daf is yud tet
י"ט. yud tet. We start at the mishna משנה. mishna. So this
is interesting to talk about how these perakim פרקים perakim transitioned because
between like where we are. You know, it's again, it's a masechet
מסכת masechet that starts a little bit off center and with this
takkana תקנה takkana bifanai nichtav ubifanai nechtam בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, bifanai
nichtav ubifanai nechtam, and you know, and you think, okay fine, we'll
deal with it in the first perek פרק, perek, and then of
course you have a whole mishna משנה mishna at the beginning of
the second perek פרק perek dealing with it as well and dealing
with variations of it. But you know, in a way it also
can be seen as a way of getting in from like indirectly
to like some of the major themes. And one of the things
that definitely emerged in the first perek פרק perek was a series
of parallels between a get גט get and a get גט get
of an isha אשה isha and a shtar shikhrur שטר שחרור shtar
shikhrur of an eved עבד. eved. And one of them was bifanai
nichtav בפני נכתב, bifanai nichtav, and to some degree that underscores the
significance that it's not just a shtar שטר. shtar. It is- it
is changing status and maybe that points to the nichtav נכתב nichtav
part about it, that there's- you know, the fact that you're testifying
that it's written is that there's special criteria relating to the writing.
So that was- so we had an interesting like collection of different
things in the first perek פרק, perek, but then- but then the,
and then as I said, the second perek פרק perek kind of
continued with the bifanai nichtav בפני נכתב, bifanai nichtav, but now we're
pulling in not things that are maybe rabbinic or special exception- well,
actually,
things-
we're using this- let me just restart that sentence again. We're using
this as a way to transition to central aspects about what ketivat
haget כתיבת הגט ketivat haget is about. So the last mishna משנה
mishna spoke about nichtav hayom venechtam balaila נכתב היום ונחתם בלילה, nichtav
hayom venechtam balaila, which again was a nice transition from bifanai nichtav
ubifanai nechtam בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. bifanai nichtav ubifanai nechtam. What if
the ketiva כתיבה ketiva and the chatima חתימה chatima were done at
different times, which really was a question about the nature of dating
of a get גט, get, and is there a special requirement, the
special requirement to put dates in a get גט get as opposed
to a shtar שטר, shtar, which the gemara גמרא gemara dealt with:
lamma hitkinu zeman begittin למה התקינו זמן בגיטין? lamma hitkinu zeman begittin?
But then also the particular psul פסול psul of a get גט
get being mukdam מוקדם, mukdam, of a get גט get being early.
So that was from a nichtav נכתב nichtav nechtam נחתם nechtam type
of an idea that got us into a central get גט get
requirement. So as opposed to the first collection, again, which was sort
of like this collection of different things: arkha'ot ערכאות arkha'ot and shtar
shikhrur שטר שחרור shtar shikhrur and shtar matana שטר מתנה shtar matana
and all these things. Here we're sort of focusing in on a
get גט. get. And now for this mishna משנה, mishna, we focus
in very specifically on the ketivat haget כתיבת הגט ketivat haget and
on the sort of de'oraita דאורייתא de'oraita requirements relating to ketivat haget
כתיבת הגט. ketivat haget. And starting us very concretely with the questions
about the physical materials that are being used. So let's take a
look at this mishna משנה. mishna. Bekhol kotvin בכל כותבין, bekhol kotvin,
you can write with everything: bediyo בדיו, bediyo, with ink; besam בסם,
besam, besikra בסיקרא- besikra sam סם sam and sikra סיקרא, sikra, which
are- well the gemara גמרא gemara will explain what they are, but
other types of
permanent inks, permanent things that will leave a permanent mark. Uvekomus ובקומוס
uvekomus uvekhankantom ובקנקנתום- uvekhankantom all these various things; ubekhol davar shehu kayyama
ובכל דבר שהוא קיימא. ubekhol davar shehu kayyama. And now anything that
lasts. But besides you'll notice there's a different girsa גרסא girsa of
this mishna משנה: mishna: bedik khol davar shehu roshem בדיק כל דבר
שהוא רושם, bedik khol davar shehu roshem, anything that leaves a mark.
Okay. So which is... could you not write it at all? Can
I do that? We'll discuss that. We will discuss etching.
But that's not stated in the mishna משנה. mishna. I mean, bedik
shehu roshem בדיק שהוא רושם bedik shehu roshem it is. Roshem רושם
roshem means an impression, doesn't it?
Yeah, but it kind of leaves a mark. I don't know. I'm
not sure if in this context roshem רושם roshem would necessarily tell
you what the story would be. You could say a roshem רושם
roshem specifically is like some type of a physical like, you know,
I don't know. It's not clear to me from this mishna משנה
mishna how you would say about carving. We'll see about that discussion
in the gemara גמרא. gemara. Ein kotvin lo bemashkin velo bemei peirot
אין כותבין לא במשקין ולא במי פירות. ein kotvin lo bemashkin velo
bemei peirot. You cannot use liquids
or fruit juices. Velo bekhol davar she'eino mitkayyem ולא בכל דבר שאינו
מתקיים, velo bekhol davar she'eino mitkayyem, which therefore the parallel would have
been shehu kayyama שהוא קיימא shehu kayyama because this is contrasting what
does work to something that eino mitkayyem אינו מתקיים, eino mitkayyem, something
that does not last. So Michael asks about something like pencil or
whatever, this raises an interesting question about what mitkayyem מתקיים mitkayyem means.
Right? Does it- how long does it have to last? Is it
a specific amount of time? A week, a month, a year, etc.?
Does it last until it's erased? Let's say something lasts, you know,
as people sometimes have- these old ketubot כתובות ketubot where-
where the stuff has started to, you know- just because of exposure
and time and air or whatever that the- you know, you can
no longer see the signatures or whatever. I mean, you know, my
mother's ketuba כתובה, ketuba, aleha hashalom עליה השלום, aleha hashalom, you know,
you say they had to get a replacement ketuba כתובה ketuba written
because- and they had a very artistic ketuba כתובה, ketuba, whatever- because
it was- the signatures had faded over time. So is there- is
there a particular, you know, amount of time or does it mean,
you know, that these types of things like the juices or whatever
as soon as they're put to paper, like it's almost instantaneous? You
know, that's not exactly clear what the shiur שיעור shiur is of
that. Yes, which might be the- the idea of the word roshem
רושם. roshem. If you say does it leave a mark, right? So
if I wrote something that like with fruit juice and like, you
know, a minute later you couldn't see it, you
would
say- Or you just saying it can't be completely like disappear immediately.
It can't be ephemeral, it can't not leave a mark? Yeah.
But קנקנתום kankantom is an iron compound that turns red, or actually
more brown, from black and it becomes less... Well, the color doesn't
matter. So we'll see about that. But right, so the issue about
pencil should not be an issue at all because that's something that
could be, it's true it could be erased,
but the idea that it has to be able to be
resist being erased is not mentioned at all, right? That's here we're
talking about things that are naturally will not last. Now, that might
be a different question about דבר שיכול להזייף. davar sheyakhol lehizayef. If
a certain pencil you could erase it and write in its place,
and that might have to do with the question about עדי מסירה
edei mesirah ועדי חתימה. v'edei hasimah. Okay. So that's the physical objects
that you write with. על הכל כותבין, al hakol kotevin, you can
write on anything, על העלה של זית, al ha'aleh shel zayit, על
הקרן של פרה. al hakeren shel parah. You can write on a
leaf of an olive
tree, and on the horn of a cow, ונותן לו את הפרה,
venoten lo et haparah, but give her the cow, don't cut off
the horn. We'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara. על יד של
עבד ונותן לו את העבד. al yad shel eved venoten lo et
ha'eved. On the arm of a slave... וכתבו ונתנו? u-khtavo venatano? וכתבו
ונתנו. ve-khtavo venatano. Yeah, except we'll see that doesn't...
that's not true fully, because וכתבו ונתנו ve-khtavo venatano means that it
can't require another act to be done. If I wrote on a
גט get and I let's say trimmed the edges off of the
גט get or something like that, it would not be a problem.
We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. ועל קרן של פרה ונותן לו
את הפרה, ve-al keren shel parah venoten lo et haparah, על יד
של עבד ונותן לו את העבד, al yad shel eved venoten lo
et ha'eved, on the hand of a slave and then you have
to give her the slave. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Yose HaGelili
omer, don't cut off the arm of the slave. רבי יוסי הגלילי
אומר אין כותבין לו על דבר שיש בו רוח חיים ולא על
אוכלים. Rabbi Yose HaGelili omer ein kotevin lo al davar she-yesh bo
ruach chayim velo al ochlim. Don't write on something that is alive,
and or neither on foods. And we'll see why in the גמרא
Gemara and we'll also see whether that's דאורייתא de-oraitta or not. So
here we're just focusing on the physical materials that a גט get
is written with and on. So the "on" it doesn't have to
last, the "with" it does. Well, again, the question is... How is
it the leaf is gonna last? Well, but okay, but that's a
good point, and that raises the same question about what does it
mean last? A leaf will last, you know, for a few days
at least, right? So if the idea is if the whole problem
is something that's completely ephemeral, then that would not be a problem
here. Let's say it was written on some type of, I don't
know, some type of a... I'm trying to imagine what the case
would be, some highly, very brittle and old paper that is falling
apart as you're handling it, and like, you know, in two minutes
it'll fall apart, maybe that wouldn't be good. Okay? It might not
be long-lasting, but that doesn't... it doesn't have to be long-lasting. Again,
that's why רושם, roshem, although it's not the logical opposite of מתקיים,
mitkayem, is a helpful word because it makes you think about the
idea that it left a mark as opposed to something that essentially
evaporated as soon as you put it on paper, and you don't
emphasize any idea of permanence. But I agree, עלה של זית aleh
shel zayit is certainly underscoring that there's not an idea here of
permanence. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. דיו,
dyo, so what's ink? דיותא. dyuta. That's ink. Good. סם, sam, what's
סם? sam? סמא. samma. So again, I don't know what these words
are, I mean, I looked at Soncino for סם, sam, I forget,
I think it said paint. רש"י Rashi says orpiment, which I have
no idea what that means. Anybody can jump in with translation that
they have. Steinsaltz says
arsenic. Steinsaltz says arsenic. Arsenic? Yeah, arsenic, in fact, The Name of
the Rose by Umberto Eco is about arsenic. As an ink? Used
in writing, yes. It poisons monks. Oh, interesting. Okay, like the lead
pencil... like lead in paint. What? What? The note here is saying
סם sam is ink derived from a grass or root. Okay, ink
derived from a grass root. Okay. סם, sam, סמא, samma, סיקרא. sikra.
What's this סיקרא? sikra? אמר רבה בר בר חנה, Amar Rabbah bar
Bar Hana, סיקראסתא שמו. sikrastah shemo. It's סיקראסתא. sikrastah. Okay, which is
basically we don't have another word for it, right? Which is this
whole problem of how to translate, what's that whole thing that Bertrand
Russell or one of those linguistic philosophers, anyway about like, you know,
what does it mean to translate a word? It's just to put
one word into other words that people are more familiar with. So
if you can't translate... how do you translate the word green? Right?
So anyway, סמא, samma, what's סמא? samma? סיקראתא. sikrata. Anyway, yeah, we
will see in the גמרא Gemara that it is red, okay, or
רש"י Rashi certainly assumes it's red. So some type of red dye.
קומוס, kumos, what's קומוס? kumos? קומא. kuma. That's קומא. kuma. There you
go. Okay, what do you got there for קומא? kuma? Gum arabic.
Gum arabic! All right. קנקנתום, kankantom, what's קנקנתום? kankantom? אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר שמואל, Amar Rabbah bar Bar Hana amar Shmuel, חרצא
דאושכפי. khartsa d'ushkhasei. Which,
what? Yeah, at least it has two words. So,
so that's some type of a, what is it? Like a coal,
a charcoal? What does it say there? The shoemaker's blacking. Shoemaker's... oh
right, that's דאושכפי. d'ushkhasei. Right, right, right. So the blacking that shoemakers
use. Some type of dye used by shoemakers. Okay. Steinsaltz says it's
copper sulfate, but it's almost certainly iron sulfate. Iron sulfate, alright, interesting.
Okay, so there you go. בכל דבר שהוא מתקיים, bekhol davar shehu
mitkayem, anything that lasts, okay? לאתויי מאי, le'atuyei mai, what does that
include? לאתויי הא דתני רבי חייא חנינא, le'atuyei ha detani rabbi chiyya
chanina, כתבו במי טריה katvo be-mei taryah if you wrote it in,
now this sounds like it is more invisible and we'll deal with
this in the Gemara, with some type of a, of some type
of a water that, what's טריה taryah mean? Rashi says מי טריה
מי גשמים לשון מורי, mei tarya mei geshamim lashon mori,
rainwater, I don't know how rainwater lasts at all, so Rashi says
מי טריה מים ששורין בו פרי שהוא כעין אפצים גאל בלא"ז, mei
tarya mayim she-shorin bo peri she-hu ke-ein afatzim gal be-la'az,
so some type of a, of you know, of a fruit or
some type of a plant was soaked in water and it gave
off its color, so it's sort of like the way that ink
is made. מי פירות? mei peirot? Well, no, מי פירות mei peirot
is like fruit juices, this is basically, this is basically the making
of a type of an ink. No, it's not plant juice, fruit
juice means you squeeze the thing and get out its natural juices,
this means you take some type of a plant that is dye
and has color and you soak it in water and you turn
it into some type of an ink.
So and אפצא aftza is, what how do they translate אפצא aftza
there? גאלנא? galna? Gallnut? Gallnut juice? And that's something that they actually
use gallnut juice and we're actually to see that that's something that
the, that they actually used to work the קלפים kelafim as well
with this gallnut juice and we'll see about that in the Gemara,
I'll read you a Tosafot. Okay, so let's take a look. So
the Gemara says like this,
okay, קשיא. kashya. So that's now תני רבי חייא, tani rabbi chiyya,
Rabbi Chiyya taught a ברייתא, braita, כתבו באבר בשחור ובשיחור כשר. katvo
be-aver bi-shachor u-vi-shichur kasher. If you wrote it in lead or in
black or in this שיחור shichur which is this shoemaker's dye, then
I think Rashi says שחור shachor might mean coal, hold on, coals,
right, פחמים, pechamim, right, so if you wrote it in lead or
coals or this shoemaker's dye it's כשר. kasher. Okay, why, I don't
know why you need that as a חידוש, chiddush, those all seem
pretty permanent to me. Okay, now איתמר, itmar, we taught a ברייתא,
braita, המדיו על גבי סיקרא בשבת. ha-madyo al gabai sikra be-shabbat. Now
here we get to an interesting conceptual discussion, if somebody put ink
on top of the סיקרא. sikra. Now remember סיקרא sikra is considered
permanent, so you had something written in סיקרא, sikra, it was however
as Charlie was telling us it is something that basically is red
or turns red, you were saying סיקרא sikra was the one that
turns red? Or קנקנתום? kankantum? Okay, whatever. Rashi says סיקרא sikra is
a reddish type of a thing, it's not as clear as distinct
as the black but it is permanent, so you now inked in
something that was written in this, okay, got it, you now inked
in something that was this reddish, I'd say this reddish and less
distinct writing and you inked it over with black, okay, you know
sometimes if you ever like play with your fonts on or your
colors in you know in Word or whatever and you turn them
into a different color and then you try to print it out,
there's a reason people use black because black on white is very
clear and distinct or whatever right, if you do it in a
color right it's not as on the screen maybe whatever, but when
you print it out so anyway you got something it's a permanent
writing but you wanted to ink it over in black, okay, so
what happens?
So so if you did it on Shabbat, Rabbi Yochanan and Reish
Lakish אמרי תרוייהו, amri taryeihu, they both חייב שתים, chayiv shtayim, you
transgressed two, how do you transgress two? אחת משום כותב achat mishum
kotev you're writing, because you're actually creating a more permanent writing although
the letters were still on it you've actually like you know made
it black letters is something better and new compared to the red
letters so you've actually done a writing, ואחת משום מוחק ve-achat mishum
mochek and what you've done is you've erased now the red ones
underneath. Now that's fascinating because you would have thought that the definition
of erase is to actually remove something rather than to cover it
up, right like this whole issue by the way you know about
lettering on cake, where the מנהג minhag going back to the מהר"ח
אור זרוע Maharach Or Zarua is like not to, not to eat
it because it would be considered a form of מוחק, mochek, רבי
עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva Eiger says that it's like it's a crazy
חומרא. chumra. But one of the questions is because it's like מתקלקל
mitkalkel and ואינו מתכוין ve-eino mitkaven and all these types of things,
but one of the questions is is that and it's what's very
frustrating is that sometimes I've seen people there's lettering on cake and
they say oh wait wait we're not allowed to eat this on
Shabbat, so what they do is they take a knife and they
and they smear away the words. Yes, which is obviously much worse,
that's like classic מוחק, mochek, that's like removing the letters as opposed
to eating you're just like destroying, right, so anyway so that's a
case so the eating of it you're not like removing the letters
you're just destroying them, but in this case you're not like destroying
you're sort of using the קלף klaf underneath and it is true
that a classic מוחק mochek is על מנת לכתוב al menat lichtov
to remove them in order to make the קלף klaf underneath usable
to write what you want to write on it, so therefore if
you want to think in terms of the קלף, klaf, you know
there is an element about מוחק mochek because what you are doing
is you have basically done something to allow you to use that
space underneath.
But it still is a bit of a חידוש, chiddush, you're just
covering up the letters, you're making them go away because something else
is covering them up and so anyway that's
considered... Really? Then it wouldn't be a חידוש chiddush at all then
you're obviously מוחק. mochek. Rashi says וזה מוחק התחתונה סיקרא וכתב העליונה
דיו. veze mochek hatachtona sikra vechtav ha'elyona deyo. I don't know, I
don't see
that they say who do they say says that? אבני נזר? Avnei
Nezer? All right, whatever, that's fine. That's not פשט pshat in the
גמרא. Gemara. But then it wouldn't be a חידוש. chiddush. Okay, so
anyway, I mean the חידוש chiddush is the first part, but it
sounds like the point there that's not פשט pshat at all. I
don't know, yeah, anyway, I don't think that's פשט pshat at all.
Okay, anyway, okay now, ואף חייב שתים אחת משום כותב ואחת משום
מוחק. ve'af chayav shtayim achat mishum kotev ve'achat mishum mochek. דיו על
גבי דיו, deyo al gabi deyo,
let's say you did it ink on top of ink. Okay, now
you could say, well, what you're doing is you're adding a fresher
ink, so therefore that is an element about כותב. kotev. You're making
it last a little longer, it's fresher ink or something. Okay? Or
סיקרא על גבי סיקרא, sikra al gabi sikra, or a red on
the red, פטור, patur, you're exempt because you did not really do
anything
qualitatively different. Now if it was fading, that's an interesting question. Let's
say it was fading ink and you re-inked something that was fading.
I don't know, that might be different, okay, because you know maybe
that would be that now it's not as clear and distinct. But
you're talking about something that is clear and distinct and all you
did was you just added a fresh coat. Okay, so then you
didn't do anything of significance. פטור. patur. Now סיקרא על גבי דיו.
sikra al gabi deyo. How about if it was the red on
top of the black? So you actually are changing it, but you're
changing it for worse. Okay? So therefore, so right, so סיקרא על
גבי דיו, sikra al gabi deyo, אמרי לה חייב ואמרי לה פטור.
amrei lah chayav ve'amrei lah patur. So some say חייב, chayav, some
say פטור. patur. אמרי לה חייב, amrei lah chayav, some say חייב,
chayav, מוחק הוא. mochek hu. You're why חייב? chayav? Not for writing
but for erasing. Okay, you are making the letters underneath not visible.
Now the problem is, well that's what you the next sentence, אמרי
לה פטור, amrei lah patur, some say you're exempt, מקלקל הוא. mekalkel
hu. Yes, you're but you're only making things worse. Meaning as opposed
to a normal מוחק, mochek, מוחק mochek you make the letters worse,
you make them go away, but you make the קלף klaf better.
You make you make the קלף klaf usable. Here the קלף klaf
is no more usable because it's got red ink on top of
it, right? It doesn't make the קלף klaf underneath anymore usable. So
you made the letters worse and you didn't make the קלף klaf
more usable. So you're so what's the position the first position and
how could it be על מנת לכתוב, al menat lichtov, right? How
could the you know besides how why isn't it מקלקל? mekalkel? Maybe
it's not מקלקל mekalkel because you prefer red, I don't know, right?
Which is an interesting question, let's say for some reason you preferred
red then it should be חייב משום כותב, chayav mishum kotev, you
know. But how is it how is it מוחק mochek without making
things worse, what did you do to be על מנת לכתוב? al
menat lichtov? So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות
Tosafot says וחשיב ליה מוחק על מנת לכתוב המוחק הוא דבתר
הכי עומד לחזור ולכתוב עליו בדיו, vechashiv leh mochek al menat lichtov
hamochek hu de'vatar hachi omed lachzor velichtov alav bedeyo, presumably you're going
to put the black do the real ink on top of it.
ומקלקל לא הוי. umekalkel lo havei. So now how did you help
things? ומקלקל לא הוי דכתובת זו תהא כתיבה עליונה רשומה ניכרת טפי,
umekalkel lo havei dechtovet zo tehei ketiva elyona reshuma nikert tefei, because
eventually your plan is to write. שפיר, Shapir, your plan is eventually
to write, but how did you help things? You didn't do and
how's it right. So תוספות Tosafot first just technically satisfied you, you
were מוחק, mochek, you made the early letters go away, and your
plan was to write, so it's על מנת לכתוב. al menat lichtov.
But how is the כותב, kotev, how was the מוחק mochek serving
the eventual כתיבה? ketiva? So that's the next point of
תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, ומקלקל לא הוי דכתיבה זו תהא כתיבה עליונה רשומה
ניכרת טפי ממעשה תחתונה לבדה. umekalkel lo havei dechtiva zo tehei ketiva
elyona reshuma nikert tefei mima'aseh tachtona levada. Somehow if you have a
this red underlay, and then on top of it you're going to
do another black layer, that'll actually make the black layer you're going
to add even better, okay? So תוספות Tosafot imagines this, I don't
know if it's true, but he's trying to explain this difficult position
that you're חייב משום מוחק. chayav mishum mochek. And he says what
you've done by adding the red is you've made the black letters
go away, and it's actually serving a good function because if you
add black on top of the red, it'll even be a better
it'll even be more distinct. That's a nice good answer that you
say, okay, so what's the position that you're פטור? patur? If that's
really true, then you really should be חייב, chayav, right? I don't
know, anyway, maybe it's not enough of a מוחק mochek because you
made the letters, I don't know. Anyway, that's their debate. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we have an interesting
discussion about applying some of this to a גט. get. בעי מיניה
ריש לקיש מרבי יוחנן. baei mineih Reish Lakish me'Rabbi Yochanan. ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish asked רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. עדים שאין יודעים לחתום מהו
שיכתבו להם בסיקרא ויחתמו. edim she'ein yode'im lachtom mahu she'yichtevu lahem besikra
ve'yachtimu. Let's say they don't know how to sign and we discussed
before making a stencil, and we're going to see that again. But
before we get to that, how about using this? How about inking
it in for them in this red ink and having them sign
over their names in the black ink? Okay? Is it like they've
added their names or would you say their names are already there?
Okay?
So, כתב עליון כתב או אינו כתב? ktav elyon ktav o eino
ktav? Is what they're adding considered writing or not considered writing? So
he says, אמר ליה אינו כתב, amar leih eino ktav, it's not
writing. אמר ליה והלא למדתנו רבנו, amar leih vehalo limadetnu rabbeinu, but
didn't our master teach us כתב עליון כתב לענין שבת? ktav elyon
ktav le'inyan Shabbat? That everybody says you're חייב chayav for שבת Shabbat
if you add this extra letter layer? So if you're חייב chayav
for שבת Shabbat it is considered a new thing that you've. done,
so you should be חייב chayav here too. So אמר ליה, Amar
lei, וכי מפני שאנו מדמים נעשה מעשה? v'chi mipnei she'anu m'damim na'aseh
ma'aseh? What? Just because we make a comparison and an analogy, do
you think that we can actually rule that way? Now this is
very interesting. What does that mean? So does that mean that any
type, I mean so much of halachic argument is done by making
analogies? Okay, so and what exactly was bothering him? So let's take
a look at רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says,
נעשה מעשה, na'aseh ma'aseh, רש"י Rashi says it's about I don't know
25 lines from the bottom, I don't know where to tell you
exactly, anyway, it starts a line, נעשה מעשה na'aseh ma'aseh in the
middle of a narrow line. Middle of the narrow lines, רש"י Rashi
says,
להקל, l'hakkel, אפילו ענין שבת, afilu inyan shabbos, are we—you think we
can be lenient to let this work for גט? get? אפילו ענין
שבת, afilu inyan shabbos, אם בא מעשה בידינו בזמן בית המקדש, im
ba ma'aseh b'yadeinu bizman beis hamikdash, if it were something that would
come at the time of the בית המקדש beis hamikdash and somebody
had done this and had written the black atop the red, לא
הייתי סומך על דברי להביא חולין לעזרה, lo hayisi somech al devarai
l'havi chullin l'azarah, I would not have relied on this to bring
when I say חייב, chayav, it means it seems to me that
it's חייב, chayav, but I wouldn't actually פסקן pasken that way, I'm
not certain. So first of all, how are we supposed to know
that? You said חייב, chayav, right? I mean, so right, what does
that mean? Any time somebody says חייב, chayav, they really mean it
just seems to me or is he just telling us? No, normally
we assume he really means it, but here he's telling us, you
know what, I really wasn't so certain. If you weren't so certain,
you should've said that you weren't so certain. But anyway, for רש"י,
Rashi, what he's really just saying is, you know what, I wasn't
really sure about my פסק. psak. Okay, which is not so interesting
and it's a little disturbing. The other way of understanding it is
that he basically saying no, no, no, by שבת shabbos I'm sure
of my פסק. psak. But I'm not sure that we can compare,
מפני זהו—this mipnei zehu is the key about the word מדמים, m'damim,
which רש"י'ס Rashi's explanation doesn't focus on. Just because—do you think just
because you can draw a line of comparison that means you can
apply what you said there to here? Maybe we can't apply that
to here. Now, why not? is the question, right? That would suggest
maybe there are different requirements by signing than there is by שבת.
shabbos. Okay, and we have to think about what those differences are,
those are different areas of הלכה halacha and maybe they have different
criteria. Now, we're in a minute we can explore what that might
be, but I do want to say that it's a very interesting
phrase. Now with Bar-Ilan you could research these things in ten seconds.
To go ahead and search in the world of halachic literature this
phrase מפני שאנו מדמים נעשה מעשה mipnei she'anu m'damim na'aseh ma'aseh is
often used when a פוסק posek is like hesitant to rule in
a particular area, like he's trying to address a new case. He
says, well, maybe you could make this following argument, dada-dada-da-da, what? But
מפני שאנו מדמים נעשה מעשה? mipnei she'anu m'damim na'aseh ma'aseh? But like
I'm not really ready to go out on a limb and to
say this way, just because I can make an argument doesn't mean
I'm going to rule that way. Of course, what sometimes that that
happens, you know, like I think there's a discussion that what do
you call it, Rabbi Yehuda Herzl Henkin sometimes in his תשובה tshuva
in בני בנים, bnei bonim, particularly sometimes around these women's issues, he
has a very interesting style. What he does is he sort of
makes a whole argument about why something should be allowed, whatever that
thing is, whether it's, I don't know, wearing a
טלית, tallis, women saying שבע ברכות, sheva brachos,
whatever the case might be, not you know, not fully covering the
hair, whatever the case might be, he makes this whole argument. And
then at the end, at the last minute he says but we
shouldn't actually, you know, מפני שאנו מדמים נעשה מעשה, mipnei she'anu m'damim
na'aseh ma'aseh, should we actually go ahead and do this just because
we can make this argument? You know, and like he pulls back
after he lays out the evidence. The issue I want to bring
out about that is not just that interesting dynamic about what does
it mean to lay out this very strong argument but then not
be willing to take the step, but that there he's making an
argument from within that area of הלכה halacha itself. Like he discusses
all the issues about hair covering and makes an argument but then
isn't willing to go the final way, or discusses the issues about
making שבע ברכות sheva brachos on a אשה. isha. You know, or
whatever the issues might be and then isn't willing to go the
final step. That's not technically, that is actually an argument, that's not
מדמה, medameh, that's not an analogy, that's actually analyzing the case itself.
Where this גמרא gemara is saying is you're making an analogy from
one area of הלכה halacha to another area of הלכה, halacha, from
הלכות שבת hilchos shabbos to הלכות hilchos signing a שטר. shtar. Those
might have different criteria. Okay, and that's a different type of a
point. That doesn't mean general halachic like, you know,
reservations about following your argument, it means about making an analogy between
two different areas of הלכה. halacha. Yes, Charlie? Two things. I actually
know someone who completed רב Rav Henkin the נשמת nishmat US program
and רב Rav Henkin refused to certify her because she didn't cover
her hair. Okay, there you go. I don't want to start getting
into politics. Yeah. But just in terms of, if you've accomplished nothing
by overwriting,
how could you possibly be חייב chayav for שבת? shabbos?
Because it was thinking, what, you have—in order to be חייב chayav
for שבת, shabbos, you have to have actually accomplished something through your
עבירה, aveirah, right?
But if you've accomplished nothing, how can you—no, you did accomplish that
it doesn't count as a good signature on a גט. get. You've
accomplished that it's now darker. You mean maybe if you did it
in a case of a גט get it would—I don't know, but
anyway, we're not talking about signing a גט get by שבת. shabbos.
We're just talking about you inked over some— some business document or
whatever, some novel or something. Yes, it's funny because ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish is addressed by רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan as דין דאתינא דרבינו.
din d'itina d'Rabino. Usually just like arguing this early earlier on in
his career he's like very respectful here. That's true. That's a good
point. Now anyway according to,
yeah,
I was just checking תוספות Tosafot who says basically the same thing
as רש"י. Rashi. So anyway in terms of why שבת Shabbat might
be different, you know, by שבת Shabbat you might have to look.
The question here is about how much, you know, by שבת, Shabbat,
by שבת Shabbat the criteria of,
you know, let me hold it off actually. We're going to get
to a שבת Shabbat discussion on the next עמוד amud and I'm
going to come back to that. For now let's just point out
that there's different, I mean not the next עמוד, amud, the next
דף daf tomorrow. For now let's just point out that there's two
different halakhic areas, הלכות שבת Hilkhot Shabbat and הלכות גט, Hilkhot Get,
and the definition of what constitutes or הלכות שטרות, Hilkhot Shtarot, what
constitutes כתיבה k'tivah for שבת Shabbat might not be the same as
what constitutes it. I guess the one thing I'll say at this
stage by way of understanding why שבת Shabbat could be more מחמיר,
machmir, you know, why you could be more חייב chayav for שבת
Shabbat and it be considered כתיבה k'tivah without being considered for the
other, is that maybe by שבת Shabbat the issue is, you know,
שבת Shabbat has an idea of אבות avot and תולדות. toldot.
And there, which a concept sort of points to the idea that
it's not necessarily always a narrowly defined action. Sometimes if you achieve
the end result it really doesn't matter how you get there, right?
So whether you bake or you cook or you do whatever, you
know, there is an idea of שינוי, shinui, but we don't have
like specific, the idea of אבות avot and תולדות toldot and categories
often tells us like anything that sort of gets any type of
an action that achieves a similar type of an end result, right?
So you could therefore another way of sort of emphasizing the end
result aspect of שבת Shabbat is the מלאכת מחשבת m'lekhet machshevet idea,
which sometimes is used to emphasize the nature of the emphasis on
the process, but sometimes is used to emphasize well as long as
it's נתקיים מחשבתו, nitkayma machshavto, you've accomplished something of significance. Okay, so
maybe a little bit something a little less downplaying of the specific
definition of process, and you know, any type of process that achieves,
you know, some the that gets this like up thing planted in
the ground or gets a tree to grow or gets a plant,
you know, whatever, it doesn't matter is it planting, is it is
it grafting, is it you know all these types of things. So
anyway there if you emphasize the result over the process, so you
could sort of could say okay in one way but if I
write something on what's already written, right, is that really you know
an act of writing? It was like you know but if I
actually change the end result by accomplishing something that now I have
like black ink instead of red ink there, right, I somehow done
something, you know I've created you know the there actually is a
different object that has resulted from what I've done. So you could
sort of could say I produced actually a חפצא דכתב, cheftza d'ksav,
maybe it wasn't so much of a like of a מעשה כתיבה.
ma'aseh k'tivah. And maybe by by the חתימת העדים, chasimat ha-edim, you
know, you could say that for them actually to sign, right, that
has to actually be considered like you're signing on something that's blank,
like for it to be considered an an classic act of like
writing. That what if I fill in something that's already red? Would
you say that I'm I'm writing these letters or you would say
like I'm inking them in, right? So you know normal writing might
require from like something that isn't there at all, right? Whereas here
you m- here you could sort of say it's less of an
act of writing but the end result results in still some something
of substance. So that's one way of thinking about it, that maybe
this type of reality of writing on top of writing is not
considered a מעשה כתיבה ma'aseh k'tivah but it does result in some
new כתב, k'sav, okay? And maybe that's the difference of שבת Shabbat
and signing.
We'll see more about
that
tomorrow. Okay,
so
the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מפני שאנו מדמין אותה כסומא. mipnei she-anu m'damin osa
k'suma. איתמר, Itmar, it was taught.
עדים שאין יודעים לחתום, edim she-ein yod'im lachtom,
now here we get to this case, they don't know how to
sign, which is why we were having the previous discussion before. רב
אמר Rav amar מקרעים להם נייר חלק m'kara'im lahem niyar chalak וממלאים
את הקרעים בדיו. u-m'mali'im et ha-k'ra'im b'dyo. You prepare for them a
stencil and they fill out the stencil with ink. Okay, that's where
תוספות Tosafot explains it certainly seems like פשט. p'shat. רש"י Rashi says
it means that you sort of... make an indentation on the קלף
klaf *klaf* and you fill the indentation with ink. ושמואל אמר באבר
*u-Shmuel amar ba-avar*. No, actually you pre-write it with some type of
lead and you write over it, which is somewhat like we're saying
before about the red, but lead would seem to be even worse.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says באבר סלקא דעתך *be-avar salka da'atach*?
You think that that could be good to first write that level
and have them write over it? והא תני רבי חייא כתבו באבר
בשחור בשיחור כשר kosher *ve-ha tani Rabbi Chiyya ketavo be-avar bishchor beshichor
kasher*. That if you write with lead it's kosher. So you see
that it's considered to be כתב ksav, *ksav*. So then you write
over it, so how could that be a new writing? And we
said before that you can't even write over the red, or at
least we're not prepared to say that that's good by the red.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא lo. קשיא *lo kashya*, it's
not difficult. הא באברא הא במיא דאברא *ha be-avara ha be-maya de-avara*.
One thing is you write with the actual lead and the other
is with some like an ink, liquid that's been turned black through
lead. Now, I would have thought that the lead leaves more of
a permanent mark than a liquid. Liquid makes me almost think it's
more transitory. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says the opposite. If you think about
the liquid that it becomes a type of an ink, that will
actually absorb into the קלף klaf *klaf* and be more permanent. If
you think about, like think about a pencil, think about the difference,
actually that's a perfect example, between a pencil and a pen. Why
is a pencil less permanent? Because it's not a liquid, it doesn't
get absorbed in, it essentially remains on the surface and therefore can
be erased, whereas ink actually is a liquid and gets absorbed in.
So if the ink actually it's not watery, it actually is a
deeply colored ink, it'll actually be more permanent. Okay, so he actually
says you can write with this pencil essentially and then ink on
top of it. Now it's nevertheless it's still a big חידוש chiddush
*chiddush* because here it gets back to the issue before about what
מתקיים *miskayem* means. If אבר aver, *avar* is considered to be not
כתב ksav *ksav* because it's erasable, or because somehow but it's still
for the time being it's definitely רושם roshem *roshem*, it definitely doesn't
go away right away, right? So the fact that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* thinks that that could be considered a legitimate signature if you
wrote on top of a lead writing, and presumably needs that what's
underneath was not yet considered to be כתב ksav, *ksav*, it's a
pretty big חידוש chiddush *chiddush* that writing with lead, essentially I think
it means like a pencil, would not be considered to be כתב
ksav. *ksav*. Okay, and that's what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says. If you
look at רש"י *Rashi* he says באבר לשפשף בחתיכה של אבר על
הקלף ומשחירה אינו כתב *be-avar leshafshef bechaticha shel avar al ha-klaf umashchirah
eino ksav*. דמיא דאברא מים ששרה בהן אפצים שחוקים *demaya de-avara mayim
she-sharah bahen afitzim shchukim* presumably that is כתב *ksav*. Okay, so that
would be a big new definition that if it's erasable essentially or
even if it does make a mark if it's not, there is
a real requirement of permanence, against what we were saying in the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. In the leaf case it wasn't permanent. Apparently you
have to say that there's some difference or I don't know, I
mean leaves can last, people preserve leaves in their picture albums, I
don't know, but he speaks specifically in עלה *aleh*. I know, but
I don't, and maybe there's a difference between the ink and the
leaf, I don't know. But I'm just saying yes, that's why I'm
pointing it out, that this is interesting. This points to the issue
about the permanence of that even if the object is somewhat permanent
even if the ink is not completely transitory. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. הא באברא והא במיא דאברא *ha
be-avara ve-ha be-maya de-avara*. רב Rav. אבא אמר
במי מילין *Rav Abba amar be-mei milin*. No, no, no, when we
said that they would write it, you write something underneath and they
write on top of it, that would be this מי מילין *mei
milin*. רש"י *Rashi* says the מי מילין *mei milin* is the, רש"י
*Rashi* says מים ששרה בהן אפצים שחוקים *mayim she-sharah bahen afitzim shchukim*,
which actually sounds like ink, these ground up gallnuts. But apparently that
was something that was considered to be not so permanent and therefore
if you wrote on top of it you're okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will have to clarify that point. והתני רב חנינא
כתבו במי טריא ואפצא כשר kosher *ve-ha tani Rav Chanina ketavo be-mei
tarya va-afatza kasher*. If you wrote it with this gallnut it's kosher,
which means it's a כתב *ksav*, so how could you say that
they could write underneath? So here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming,
notice before it said we can't be מדמה *medameh* to שבת Shabbos
*Shabbos*. But what it is assuming that they could be מדמה *medameh*
is what constitutes a כתב *ksav* for גט get, *get*. If it's
not a כתב *ksav* for גט get *get*, it does work to
be the underlying layer on top of which the עדים eidim *edim*
write. That's also being מדמה *medameh*. How do you know the definition
of a כתב *ksav* for גט get *get* automatically translates into whether
the עדים eidim *edim* can write on top of it or whatever?
That they're willing to assume. Okay, so they say one minute, if
this אפצים *afitzim* counts as כתב *ksav* for גט get *get*, then
the עדים eidim *edim* can't write on top of it, that's not
considered a חתימה *chatimah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא קשיא
*lo kashya*. הא דעפיץ הא דלא עפיץ *ha de-afitz ha de-lo afitz*.
It depends whether the קלף *klaf* was worked with this gallnut juice
or not, and that's what תוספות *Tosafot* discusses it well. If the
קלף *klaf* was worked with the gallnut juice and then they write
on top of it with a gallnut mixture, it won't be visible,
it won't really leave a distinct mark. שאין מי מילין על גבי
מי מילין *she-ein mei milin al gabei mei milin*, because it won't
leave a distinct mark. And then it's just like all the other
cases in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* of something that evaporates. So here
it wouldn't evaporate on a different piece of paper, on a different
piece of paper it would leave a permanent mark, but on a
קלף *klaf* that's been worked with this, that's been treated with this,
it's not going to be distinct. So basically what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says is there could be a case for שבת *Shabbos* of
inking on top where you're חייב chayav *chayav*, but we're not prepared
to say that works for עדים eidim *edim*, so we're going to
assume an underlying layer. so maybe there are different criteria, so we're
going to assume for the signing of עדים eidim. the thing underneath
can't constitute כתב, and where the definition about that is going to
be what constitutes כתב for the writing of a גט, get okay,
and therefore the cases where it would be allowed is if the
stuff underneath is not permanent or in this case doesn't leave a...
isn't ניכר, nikkar, doesn't leave a רושם because of the קלף that
it's being written on. But the big חידוש chiddush about this is
the case of the אבר, the lead, that if you write something
on lead which is essentially doesn't get absorbed in, essentially is like
pencil, right, the חידוש is that that sounds like that actually doesn't
constitute כתב, which is a big חידוש because then the question comes
how permanent does something have to be and what's the definition of
being permanent? So if I wrote it on black... if I wrote
it with black ink on black paper, yeah, still wouldn't be good.
Correct. But if I did it on שבת would I be חייב
or not? No. Neither... either way. Yeah, there are cases obviously which
cut across the board. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Yes. Black on black...
how would you see it? No, yeah, well that's exactly the point.
Okay, that's what... חברה, Chevra,
we have 15 minutes, let's go. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: רב פפא אמר. Rav Pappa amar.
ברוק, be-rok, no, here's what he how he would handle it if
עדים needed to be, you know, to sign and they couldn't sign
their names, is he would use spit. Okay, וכן אורי ליה רב
פפא לפפא תורא. vechen orei lei Rav Pappa le-Pappa tura. This was
רב פפא Rav Pappa showed to this
other guy, to this guy whose name was פפא Pappa who worked
with the oxen or whatever, ox-seller, ברוק be-rok he would, he showed
him to do, like, you know, use your spit and then have
the עדים write on top of the spit. Okay, והני מילי בגיטין.
vehanei milei be-gitten. Now, when do we allow something like this? So
even... so this is a special exception because we're allowing עדים who
don't know how to sign their names, and as was pointed out,
it's a problem because you can't recognize their signatures. Okay, so when
do we allow something like this? And even what we're allowing is
when the bottom thing is not real כתב. When do we allow
something like that? We allow it with גיטין. gitten. אבל בשטרות לא,
aval bi-shtaros lo, not בשטרות. bi-shtaros. Okay, because by גיטין gitten there's
an עגונה agunah problem, as we'll see in a minute. Okay, as
רש"י says: בגיטין משום עגונה כדלקמן דלא משכחינא סהדי בקי בתוך כך
יפרש זה לים ימות ותזקק ליבום. be-gitten mishum agunah ke-dilekamman delo meshkachina
sahedi be-ki be-tokh kakh yafaresh zeh le-yamam yamut ve-tizakkek le-yibbum. Okay, so
therefore by an עגונה, agunah, right, what's the עגונה? agunah? She won't
get... so he won't divorce her. But what do you mean? Sometimes
he needs to divorce her and sometimes the absence of divorcing when
a divorce is necessary is considered עגונה. agunah. Hello, which is exactly
our עגונה agunah cases. Okay, but anyway and the case would be
that he's going to be going away far away, right, and therefore
and he might
not come back and she'll never know if he's alive or dead
and she'll be an עגונה agunah her whole life, or even just
a יבום yibbum case is considered משום עגונה. mishum agunah. He'll die
and then the brother-in-law, it'll be impossible to find the brother-in-law and
to get him to come do the יבום yibbum etc. So all
of those are cases where it's deemed that a גט get, is
necessary and the absence of providing one is considered an עגונה agunah
case. Okay, now, but that's not by שטרות, shtaros, because okay, you
can't lend the guy a thousand dollars till you find כשר kosher,
witnesses, find the כשר kasher. witnesses, all right. I mean not כשר,
kosher but witnesses that know how to sign their name.
ההוא דעבד עובדא בשאר שטרות. hahu de-avid uvda bi-shear shtaros. There's a
guy who actually it was a different type of a שטר shtar
and he helped the witnesses sign their name, he used spit or
whatever, ונגדיה רב כהנא. ve-nagdei Rav Kahana. רב כהנא Rav Kahana gave
him lashes. Okay, he thought that was מעין גט, me'ein get, you
could understand it also because as Michael was saying, the whole idea
of קיום, kiyum, of validating signatures, right, in monetary matters, right, you
know if you allowed this type of a thing of signatures that
were not identifiable, you could rob somebody blind, right? You'd just sign
your own thing and you just say well I know you can't
recognize those signatures, they look like block letters because we used stencils
because it was whatever, so you could write up your own שטרות
shtaros with that if you did it with other things. Right, by
גט which is about not about, you know, as I said the
first רמב"ן Ramban that I mentioned to you on the מסכת masekhta
says, it's not about like two sides in a debate and it's
about an issue about you know taking property... it's not about taking
property away from somebody, it's about an issue of personal status. So
yeah, I mean is there a theoretical problem a woman could write
her own גט and say here, yes, but again it's seen as
maybe less of an issue. It's much more focuses on personal status.
So that's another reason. It's the flip side of משום עגונה. mishum
agunah. It's the... what would be the societal consequences of allowing something
like this בשאר שטרות. bi-shear shtaros. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרב. tanya ke-vateih
de-Rav. We taught like רב. עדים שאין יודעים לחתום, eidim she-ein yodeim
lakhtom, if witnesses don't know how to sign, מקרעי לה נייר חלק,
mekarei lah niar halak, you cut out a stencil, וממלא את הקרעים
דיו u-memallei et ha-keraim dyo and you fill it with ink. אמר
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, במה דברים אמורים
בגיטי נשים, be-meh devarim amurim be-gittei nashim, that's true by גיטין gitten
for what... for women. אבל בשחרור עבדים, aval bi-shichrur avadim, now here's
a case of עבדים avadim which is a... which is the intersection
of ממונות mammonus and personal status, okay. Imagine that an עבד eved
who's literate, right, he can just write you know just oh well
there were stenciled signatures on my שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, okay, ובשאר
כל השטרות u-vi-shear kol ha-shtaros and all other documents, אם יודעים לקרוא
ולחתום חותמים, im yodeim likro ve-lakhtom khosmim, if they know how to
read and sign they can, ואם לאו אין חותמים, ve-im lav ein
חותמים, and if not they can't. So it's only something that we
allow by גיטין. gitten. So that statement we're going to get to
it... I mean that statement that we allow by גיטין... gitten... That
same, that statement that we allowed only by גיטין Gittin was consistent
with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this: קריאה מאן דכר שמה, kria man dchar shema, who mentioned the
idea of reading? How does that play in? חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני,
chasurei mechasra vehachi katanei, it's missing words in here's how you have
to read it. עדים שאין יודעים לקרות, eidim she'ein yodim likros, if
they don't know how to read, קוראין לפניהם וחותמין, korin lifneihem vechotmin,
then you can actually read it for them and tell them what's
written in it. ובשאין יודעים לחתום, uveshein yodim lachtom, and if they
don't know how to sign, you can give them a stencil. So
they can be completely illiterate, you tell them what's written, you give
them a stencil and they sign it, and all of that is
כשר. kosher Now that seems like a pretty big leniency. They don't
know what's in it, and you can't even recognize. Now the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says by everything. Then אמר רב שמעון בן גמליאל,
amar Rav Shimon Ben Gamliel, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben
Gamliel says: No, I agree with you we allow those two things
by גיטין, Gittin, במה דברים אמורים בגיטי נשים אבל בשחרורי עבדים ובשאר
כל השטרות אם יודעים לקרות ולחתום חותמין ואם לאו אין חותמין. bameh
devarim amurim begittei nashim aval beshichrurei avadim uveshear kol hashtarot im yodim
likros velachtom chosmin ve'im lav ein chosmin. And all of that makes
an enormous amount of sense, right? Because imagine how you could trick
witnesses into signing something by telling them what's written and so on.
So by something that's about a טוען ונטען to'ein venit'an like
take and it's a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot type of a thing,
the societal consequences is obviously we cannot allow that type of stuff.
גיטי נשים, gittei nashim, on the other hand, the societal consequences is
seen as less severe that it'll be abused, and you also have
the עגונה agunah situation where we're going to allow that. So that's
רבן שמעון גמליאל's Rabban Shimon Gamliel split. So אמר רב אלעזר, amar
Rav Elazar, מאי טעמא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, mai ta'ama deRabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel, what's the reason? שלא יהו בנות ישראל עגונות, shelo yehu
bnot yisrael agunot, that you're not leave them as עגונות, agunot, emphasizing
what makes גיטין Gittin special. You could also have emphasized what also
makes the שאר שטרות shear shtarot so consequential. Now, אמר רבא, amar
Rava, says רבא, Rava, הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, halacha keRabban Shimon
Ben Gamliel, we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon Ben
Gamliel. All right now, which is
good, it makes sense, it's good that we keep it by גיטין
Gittin and it makes sense that we don't, aren't so lenient by
שאר שטרות. shear shtarot. So the גמרא Gemara, says, ורב גמדא משמיה
דרבא אמר אין הלכה, veRav Gamda mishmei deRava amar ein halacha, we
don't rule like him. Presumably it works by all שטרות shtarot to
do this type of stuff. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואלא כמאן
כרבנן, ve'ela keman kerabbanan, you want to go like the rabbis? וההוא
דעבד עובדא בשאר שטרות ונגדיה רב כהנא, vehahu de'avad uvda beshear shtarot
venagdei Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav Kahana gave lashes to a guy
that did this stuff with שאר שטרות. shear shtarot. So it seems
pretty clear we want to assume that רב גמדא Rav Gamda isn't
going against רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, especially if רב כהנא Rav Kahana
was so drastic to give lashes to somebody who did this, he
obviously felt that this was an institution that needed to be protected.
Right? Like I said, what, it wasn't even a חטא? chet? Like
what, it wasn't like he אכל חלב achal cheilev or something? Like
it wasn't like he did, it was a, but maybe רב כהנא
Rav Kahana felt like, no, this would be disastrous to the institution
of שטרות shtarot if we let this thing happen. So how could
רב גמדא Rav Gamda say that we actually say it's allowed? So
the גמרא Gemara says, תרגמה אקריאה. targema akria. No, no, when he
said that we allow it by שאר שטרות, shear shtarot, it was
not that we allow signing something if you don't know how to
sign, it was that we allow you to have somebody else read
it for you. Now that's surprising, because if I had to say
which one would I rather allow by שאר שטרות, shear shtarot, well,
I don't know. On the one hand, I could say I could
always just tell the עדים that something is written and get them
to sign if you let me read it, I could dupe them
into it. On the other hand, if we're talking about a guy
that's being dishonest, then you're leaving up a much bigger opportunity if
you're saying that the signatures don't have to be recognizable, you can
use stencils because then everybody could just print their own שטרות shtarot
and use stencils and say the witnesses did it, no, here are
the signatures. Why do they
look like block letters? Yeah, because the
guys
didn't
know how to sign
their name. Right? So in terms of the cause, the potential abuse,
not having to have recognizable signatures is a much larger potential abuse
than allowing me to read it and have them trust me that
I'm reading it. So that's what he says. He says, what I
will allow by שאר שטרות, shear shtarot, I agree with you, we
cannot allow unrecognizable signatures, block letter signatures. What we can allow by
שאר שטרות shear shtarot is to have somebody else read it to
the עדים. Now, how are we going to get to know that
that reading was accurate? So that's now what the גמרא Gemara is
going to turn to, is like how can we trust what's being
read? So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: לא צריכא אלא בשאר שטרות. lo tzricha ela beshear shtarot. תרגמה
אקריאה. targema akria. רב יהודה מצטער קרי וחתים. Rav Yehuda mitzta'er kari
vechatim. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda discomforted himself in order to read it,
maybe his eyes were going bad and they didn't have glasses. So
but he would squint in order to read it before he would
sign any document. He wanted to read it himself. Because he's like
saying, like maybe he's פוסק posek like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban
Shimon Ben Gamliel, that you can't have anybody read it. So אמר
ליה עולא לא צריכא, amar lei Ulla lo tzricha, you don't need,
you can have other people read it. דהא רב אלעזר מארי דארץ
ישראל. deha Rav Elazar marei de'eretz yisrael. רב אלעזר Rav Elazar who
was considered the master of Israel because he was so authoritative, particularly
in areas of כתמים, ketamim, discusses the גמרא Gemara and so on,
and maybe also specifically relates to the fact that he had good
eyesight there because that was about looking at colors about stains and
what not. And nevertheless,
קרו קמיה וחתים, karu kamei vechatim, he had other people read the
document for him and then he would sign it. ורב נחמן קרו
קמיה ספרי דייני וחתים, veRav Nachman karu kamei safrei dayanei vechatim, and
רב נחמן Rav Nachman had... The scribes of the דיינים dayanim read
a document before him and he would sign it. But then the
גמרא Gemara pulls back a little bit, like why? Okay, so this
sounds like we're going like רב גמדא, Rav Gamda, like we actually
allow by גיטין. Gittin. The thing that we allow only by גיטין
Gittin is if you don't have a recognizable signature. But when it
comes to having that, we're only allowed by גיטין Gittin because it's
such a potential for abuse. But when it talks about having other
people read it for you, that we'll allow by שטרות. shtarot. But
now the גמרא's Gemara pulling back. To be more lenient by שטרות?
shtarot? No, we'll also allow by שטרות. shtarot. By גיטין Gittin we
allow both somebody to read and a non-recognizable signature,
but by רב שמעון Rav Shimon we would allow neither by שטרות.
shtarot. Right. We are saying by שטרות shtarot we won't allow you
to like sign if you don't know how to sign, you have
to sign with your own handwriting, but what we will allow is
somebody else to read it for you. So now after these stories,
even if somebody who knows how to read, right, so the גמרא,
Gemara that's why the גמרא Gemara gave these examples, you know, but
now the גמרא Gemara pulls back a little bit because that also
had a, right, because that also has a potential for abuse. So
now the גמרא's Gemara going to pull back. ודווקא רב נחמן וספרי
דייני. vedavka Rav Nachman vesafrey dayaney. The only thing would be רב
נחמן Rav Nachman to combine with these scribes of the דיינים, dayanim,
דאית להו
אימתא, de'it lehu eimta, that they're afraid of him and they wouldn't
lie. אבל רב נחמן וספרי אחריני aval Rav Nachman vesafrey achriney or
רב נחמן Rav Nachman and other, you know, sort of scribes,
ספרי דייני ואינשי אחריני safrey dayaney ve'inshey achriney and others, לא. So
it's pretty amazing that the scribes of the judges would misrepresent the
שטר shtar to other people, but anyway here the גמרא is pulling
back. So the גמרא basically says, you know, by other שטרות shtarot
it's okay to have somebody else read, but then all of a
sudden limits it to cases where you're like pretty darn confident that
the person is afraid of lying. Now you could have, what was
the גמרא thinking before it made this qualification? Right? Like the case
about
the case where, you know, what was the case just before about
about רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who was squinting and עולא Ulla said
you don't have to? Right. So why was that the, you know,
why was that a similar case? Like like how could how could
how could he have been certain, I'm sorry, who again was squinting?
רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. How could רב יהודה Rav Yehuda have been
certain that they were reading it accurately before him? Right? So I
don't know, maybe עולא Ulla says, hey, you know, רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, I'll read it for you. You can trust me. Okay. But
now the גמרא is like pulling back and limiting it to cases
where the person who's reading you can know you can trust them.
Now before it made that qualification presumably there would be a reason
why you might be able to say that. Why might you be
able to say that it's okay to have somebody read a document
that you didn't read and you sign it, you know, and that
even if even if it's not somebody that you know would be
afraid to lie to you and you and so on? Because you
could have at least said, if you can read you can check
it. Well, it's מילתא דעבידא לאגלויי, milta de'avida le'igluyey, meaning if it's
right there, the document itself, you could say, well, somebody else won't
lie, I can always take this document and show it to somebody
else, right, to, and you know, and so on. But nevertheless the
גמרא is saying, thinks still about the abuse. It's me and you
in this room, I'm telling you what it says, yeah it says
that Michael borrowed ten thousand dollars from me or or whatever, and
I don't say that, says I'm borrowing ten thousand dollars from Michael.
Go ahead, you see it says Michael's name, you see it says
my name, you see it says ten thousand, that's what it says,
go ahead and sign it. Of course, I'm having it say that
he borrowed some money from me, not that I'm borrowing the money
from him. Okay. So even if in theory you could take it
and show it to somebody else to read it, you're not going
to, you're going to sign it, right, so it is this serious
potential of abuse. So in the גמרא and the גמרא pulls it
back and limits it to cases where you really can trust the
person. Okay so now the גמרא says like this.
רב פפא כי הוו אתו לקמיה שטר פרסאה. Rav Pappa ki havu
atu lekamey shtar parsa'ah. Now when רב פפא Rav Pappa had a
document written in Persian come in front of him, דעבידי בערכאות, de'avidi
be'arka'ot, that was done in the ערכאות arka'ot של כותים shel kutim
of the Samaritans or של גוים shel goyim it probably is. Anyway
yeah, של גוים. shel goyim. So basically if you remember an early
משנה was about documents that were done in the non-Jewish courts which
basically were valid because fundamentally they just proved that a transaction took
place. They're not about personal status, they're just about evidence and we
assume that these courts are actually honest courts and this document is
good evidence even if it doesn't work as a שטר, shtar, it's
good evidence that a transaction took place. So מקרי להו, makrey lehu,
so the fact that it was כשר kosher, that was an early
משנה. But how did he know what was written in it? He
didn't know the
language. So מקרי להו לשני כותים makrey lehu lishney kutim זה שלא
בפני זה. zeh shelo bifney zeh. He would have two non-Jews read
it not in each other's presence. Okay. It's sort of like, you
know, and compare, translate this document for me and then compare their
translations. And if they were the same translation and they weren't in
each other's presence, he knew that, you know, what else could it
be except that's what it was saying? Now במסיח לפי תומו, bemasiach
lefi tumo, if they were just talking to their innocence, which means
like, now what does מסיח לפי תומו? masiach lefi tumo? Why do
you want a translation other than you want a translation? What does
it mean? Well we're just שמוזינג. schmoozing. No, but what it probably
means is is that he took like random non-Jews off the street,
people who did not know the particulars of the case. So if
they weren't, what else, how, there would be no other way the
two random translations would match if they were people that were uninvolved
in the case. Okay. And once he figured out No, but what
it probably means is that he took like random non-Jews off the
street, people who did not know the particulars of the case. So
if they weren't, what else, how there would be no other way
that two random translations would match if they were people that were
uninvolved in the case. Okay, and once he figured out what it
meant, ומגבי ביה ממשעבדי, u-magvi bei mi-meshabedi, he would use it to
collect even from property that had a lien on it, he would
so much trust it as a legitimate translation and as a legitimate
שטר. shtar. And the idea of משעבדי meshabedi is also, if I
borrow money from Michael, Michael has a lien on my property. That
lien, the reason that lien occurs only by a שטר shtar is
because the שטר shtar becomes a matter of record and other people
know about it, and therefore the buyers of people who buy my
property are aware of the lien, right? You wouldn't, so you need
there to be a שטר shtar so that they can be aware
of that lien. So what he was saying was even if it
was a Persian שטר, shtar, a non-Jewish שטר, shtar, and so on,
if it was a matter of record, which is interesting that people
could find out about by getting it translated, even though it was
in a foreign language, right, nevertheless that was enough that he said
it was not only legitimate, but that actually the liens would be
in effect. Okay, let me just add, I know we're a little
over, let me just read one other sentence. אמר רב אשי אמר
לי רב הונא בר נתן הכי אמר אמימר. Amar Rav Ashi amar
li Rav Huna bar Natan hachi amar Ameimar. This is what אמימר
Ameimar said: האי שטרא פרסאה, Hai shtar'a parsa'ah,
this Persian שטר, shtar, which is basically רש"י says this is now
we're no longer dealing with ערכאות, arka'ot, it's not coming from the
non-Jewish courts, it was written by Jews but it was written in
Persian. Okay, דחתימי עליה סהדי ישראל De-chatimi alei sahadei Yisrael and has
Jewish signatures, so it's כשר kosher. except that it's written in a
foreign language. מגבינן ביה ממשעבדי, Magbinan bei mi-meshabedi, it's a good שטר
shtar and you collect from liens. Gemara says one minute, והלא לא
ידעי למקרי, Ve-halo lo yad'ei le-mikri, you don't, but how could we
do it, we don't know what the language, we can't read that
language. בידוע, Be-yadu'a, we're talking about people who can read it or
like the case like before that you get it read in a
way that you can trust. Obviously the common denominator here is you're
not reading it yourself, you're not the witness here, here you're the
דיין, dayan, okay, but you're not reading it yourself but you're having
it read for you in a way that you can trust. Okay,
והבעינן כתב שאינו יכול להזדייף והליכא, Ve-ha ba'inan ketav she-eino yachol le-hizdayef
ve-leika,
it has to be writing that can't be forged. Apparently they would,
if it's done by people who don't know what they're doing, they
would often use an ink that you could erase and write over
it and change the particulars from ten thousand to a hundred thousand,
okay, so that's a problem here. Gemara says והליכא בדפיצנא. Ve-leika bi-defitzna.
No, the קלף was worked with this gall nut and therefore it
cannot be erased. So even though it was done by these less,
by these people that did it in Persian, that doesn't mean they
didn't follow the right הלכות. halachot. Okay, so the Gemara says והא
בעינן צריך לחזור מעניינו של שטר בשיטה אחרונה והליכא, Ve-ha ba'inan tzarich
lachzor me-inyano shel shtar be-shitah achronah ve-leika, you have to go ahead
and repeat the idea of the שטר shtar in the last line,
mention at the end of the שטר shtar the basic essence of
the שטר. shtar. Again, and you don't have it. It was assuming
that these documents that were done not through the Jewish courts would
not have these criteria satisfied even if they were done by Jews.
And the Gemara says דאהדריה, De-ahadreih, you did it, you repeated the
last line. So basically you're talking about a שטר shtar that's a
hundred percent like a Jewish שטר, shtar, it's written by Jews, a
hundred percent like הלכה. halachah. The only difference is it's written in
Persian. So the Gemara says אלא מאי קא משמע לן, Ela mai
ka mashma lan, so what are you telling me? דכל לשון כשר,
De-chol lashon kasher, that you can write in other languages? תנינא. Tenina.
גט שכתבו עברית ועדיו יוונית, Get she-katvo Ivrit ve-adav Yevanit,
even a גט that's written in Hebrew or יוונית ועדיו עברית Yevanit
ve-adav Ivrit or Greek and signed in Hebrew, כשר, it's כשר. So
the Gemara says no, אי מההיא הוה אמינא, Ei me-hahi hava amina,
if it was just for that I would have said הני מילי
בגיטין, Hani milei be-gittin, that's by a גט, okay, where we're more
or less give more latitude, אבל בשאר שטרות לא קא משמע לן,
Aval bi-shear shtarot lo ka mashma lan, but not by other שטרות.
shtarot. Okay, and by other שטרות shtarot I would have said maybe
we're again, like we've seen, we're more limited, קא משמע לן Ka
mashma lan that it's okay if it's written in another language. So
basically what we've said here is that by גיטין gittin we allow
others to read it and even to sign something that's not a
recognizable signature. By שאר שטרות shear shtarot we do not allow others
to sign a signature if they cannot sign their own signature because
obviously that's enormous abuse. Do we allow others to read it by
שאר שטרות? shear shtarot? First the Gemara says yes, okay, but then
it pulls back a bit and it says we're only going to
allow that also is given to abuse by שאר שטרות, shear shtarot,
right, you could rob somebody blind if you get some trusting witnesses.
So we only allow it in cases where the person really very
limited circumstances where the reading is done in a way where you're
absolutely certain that you're getting an accurate report about what's written in
the שטר. shtar. Okay.